Guide to the Werner Brandt Papers 1951-1983 (Bulk 1956-1983) MC.13
New York University Archives
Werner Brandt Papers
1951-1983
New York University Archives
Brandt, W. (Werner)
Yamus, Leonard
MC.13
1.6 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in a shared manuscript box.
Werner Brandt was a professor of physics at New York University from 1961-1966. From 1967 onward, he was also the director of the university's Radiation and Solid State Physics Laboratory. Brandt was a pioneer in research on energy, matter, and radiation. This collection is comprised of his articles and reports from the period of 1951 to 1983.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Professor Leonard Yamus at an unknown date. The accession number associated with this gift is 84.021. An accretion was added in 2022.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by date.
Biographical Note
Werner Brandt was a professor of physics at New York University and the director of its Radiation and Solid State Physics Laboratory. He headed research that investigated atomic radiation and solid state physics. Brandt was also an enthusiastic advocate of the arts and supported interdependence between science and humanities.
Brandt was born in Kiel, Germany on May 19, 1925. His mother was descended from a long line of scientists, philosophers, and physicians, and both his grandfather and father taught at the University of Heidelberg. Brandt received his bachelor's degree (1948), his master's (1950), and his PhD (1951) from Heidelberg. In 1951, Brandt also began working with Niels Bohr at the University Institute of Theoretical Physics in Copenhagen. It was there that Brandt became interested in research on the interaction of charged particles with matter. Brandt joined the Dupont Research Laboratories in Wilmington, Delaware in 1952, with the purpose of exploring the uses of atomic waste. In 1957, Brandt became a United States citizen. As leader of research in the Dupont Radiation Physics Laboratory, Brandt concluded that atomic wastes were dangerous to the environment.
Brandt's research shifted from the industrial setting to the academic. From 1961-1966, he was an associate professor of physics at New York University. Here, Brandt helped plan, build, and direct (from 1967 onward) the Radiation and Solid State Laboratory. While in this capacity, he investigated the interactions of matter with energy (light, electrons, positrons, heavily charged particles, etc.). Brandt conducted research on the collective effects in atoms, on inner shell excitation of atoms by swift ions, and on energy losses by swift ion clusters in solids. He was also an expert in thermalization and diffusion of positrons in solids and on the behavior of positrons in molecular substances. Besides being director of the lab, Brandt was also Chairman of the Physics Department from 1967-1968.
Brandt taught at the University of Pennsylvania (1958-1960), the University of California at San Diego, and at the universities of Aarhus, Munich, Grenoble, and Paris. From 1962-1969, Brandt maintained close ties to the French National Institute for Scientific and Nuclear Techniques and Swedish scientific and technical industries. He was Nordita Professor at the Institute of Theoretical Physics at Chalmers Technical University in Gothenburg from 1963-1964.
In 1982, he was senior management and scientific consultant to Eka AB, a chemical company. He was also associated with Oak Ridge and Brookhaven National Laboratories, Grumman Laboratories, and NASA. Brandt's other accomplishments include receiving the Humboldt award in 1978 for scientific research and public services and being a fellow of the American and European Physical Societies.
Werner Brandt died of cancer in Sweden on 1 January 1983. At the time of his death, Brandt was nominated for the Legion d'Honneur. He is remembered for his research on matter, energy, and radiation, as well as his interests in music, art, and literature.
Scope and Contents
This collection houses the articles, writings, and reports by Werner Brandt. A majority of the articles come from the Physical Review. Included in the collection is one of Brandt's first publications, his translation of a 1669 treatise on Icelandic crystals by his ancestor, Erasmus Bartholinus. Materials date from 1951 to 1983.
Physics; Yamus, Leonard; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962; Bartholin, Erasmus, 1625-1698; University of California, San Diego; Universität Heidelberg; University of Pennsylvania; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science
- Inventory
  - Erasumus Bartholinus, Experiments With the Double Refracting Iceland Crystal (translated by Werner Brandt), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Ceremony on Werner Brandt, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper and an Article Based On His Research, 1959,1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NYU Department of Physics - Research Reports, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1951-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Physical Review A (Scattered Issues), 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Physical Review B (Scattered Issues), 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Physical Review Letters (Scattered Issues), 1963-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Presentations, 1963-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Research Report, 1957,1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Publications and Articles, 1951-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7-8, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publications and Articles, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2-4, Box Shared University Archives 073, Folder 17)
  - Publications and Articles, 1974-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)